<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-dots-multihoming-latest"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DOTS Multihoming">Multi-homing Deployment Considerations
    for Distributed-Denial-of-Service Open Threat Signaling (DOTS)</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wei Pan" initials="W." surname="Pan">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>william.panwei@huawei.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document discusses multi-homing considerations for
      Distributed-Denial-of-Service Open Threat Signaling (DOTS). The goal is
      to provide some guidance for DOTS clients/gateways when multihomed.</t>

      <!--
-->
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In many deployments, it may not be possible for a network to
      determine the cause of a distributed Denial-of-Service (DoS) attack
      <xref target="RFC4732"></xref>. Rather, the network may just realize
      that some resources appear to be under attack. To help with such
      situations, the IETF has specified the DDoS Open Threat Signaling (DOTS)
      architecture <xref target="RFC8811"></xref>, where a DOTS client can
      inform an upstream DOTS server that its network is under a potential
      attack and that appropriate mitigation actions are required. The DOTS
      protocols can be used to coordinate real-time mitigation efforts which
      can evolve as the attacks mutate, thereby reducing the impact of an
      attack and leading to more efficient responsive actions. <xref
      target="RFC8903"></xref> identifies a set of scenarios for DOTS; most of
      these scenarios involve a Customer Premises Equipment (CPE).</t>

      <t>The high-level base DOTS architecture is illustrated in <xref
      target="arch"></xref> (<xref target="RFC8811"></xref>):</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="arch" title="Basic DOTS Architecture">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+-----------+            +-------------+
| Mitigator | ~~~~~~~~~~ | DOTS Server |
+-----------+            +-------------+
                                |
                                |
                                |
+---------------+        +-------------+
| Attack Target | ~~~~~~ | DOTS Client |
+---------------+        +-------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8811"></xref> specifies that the DOTS client may be
      provided with a list of DOTS servers; each of these servers is
      associated with one or more IP addresses. These addresses may or may not
      be of the same address family. The DOTS client establishes one or more
      DOTS sessions by connecting to the provided DOTS server(s) addresses
      (e.g., by using <xref target="RFC8973"></xref>).</t>

      <t>DOTS may be deployed within networks that are connected to one single
      upstream provider. It can also be enabled within networks that are
      multi-homed. The reader may refer to <xref target="RFC3582"></xref> for
      an overview of multi-homing goals and motivations. This document
      discusses DOTS multi-homing considerations. Specifically, the document
      aims to:<list style="numbers">
          <t>Complete the base DOTS architecture with multi-homing specifics.
          Those specifics need to be taken into account because: <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Sending a DOTS mitigation request to an arbitrary DOTS server
              Will not necessarily help in mitigating a DDoS attack. </t>

              <t>Blindly forking all DOTS mitigation requests among all
              available DOTS servers is suboptimal.</t>

              <t>Sequentially contacting DOTS servers may increase the delay
              before a mitigation plan is enforced.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Identify DOTS deployment schemes in a multi-homing context, where
          DOTS services can be offered by all or a subset of upstream
          providers.</t>

          <t>Provide guidelines and recommendations for placing DOTS requests
          in multi-homed networks, e.g.,: <list style="symbols">
              <t>Select the appropriate DOTS server(s).</t>

              <t>Identify cases where anycast is not recommended for DOTS.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document adopts the following methodology: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Identify and extract viable deployment candidates from <xref
          target="RFC8903"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Augment the description with multi-homing technicalities, e.g.,
          <list style="symbols">
              <t>One vs. multiple upstream network providers</t>

              <t>One vs. multiple interconnect routers</t>

              <t>Provider-Independent (PI) vs. Provider-Aggregatable (PA) IP
              addresses</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Describe the recommended behavior of DOTS clients and gateways
          for each case.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Multi-homed DOTS agents are assumed to make use of the protocols
      defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-rfc8782-bis"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC8783"></xref>; no specific extension is required to the base
      DOTS protocols for deploying DOTS in a multi-homed context.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC8811"></xref> and <xref target="RFC4116"></xref>. In
      particular: </t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Provider-Aggregatable (PA) addresses">are
          globally-unique addresses assigned by a transit provider to a
          customer. The addresses are considered "aggregatable" because the
          set of routes corresponding to the PA addresses are usually covered
          by an aggregate route set corresponding to the address space
          operated by the transit provider, from which the assignment was made
          (Section 2 of <xref target="RFC4116"></xref>).</t>

          <t hangText="Provider-Independent (PI) addresses">are
          globally-unique addresses which are not assigned by a transit
          provider, but are provided by some other organisation, usually a
          Regional Internet Registry (RIR) (Section 2 of <xref
          target="RFC4116"></xref>).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>IP indifferently refers to IPv4 or IPv6.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="msc" title="Multi-Homing Scenarios">
      <t>This section describes some multi-homing scenarios that are relevant
      to DOTS. In the following subsections, only the connections of border
      routers are shown; internal network topologies are not elaborated.</t>

      <t>This section distinguishes between residential CPEs vs. enterprise
      CPEs because PI addresses may be used for enterprises while this is not
      the current practice for residential CPEs.</t>

      <section anchor="sc1" title="Multi-Homed Residential Single CPE">
        <t>The scenario shown in <xref target="rcpe"></xref> is characterized
        as follows: <list style="symbols">
            <t>The home network is connected to the Internet using one single
            CPE.</t>

            <t>The CPE is connected to multiple provisioning domains (i.e.,
            both fixed and mobile networks). Provisioning domain (PvD) is
            explained in <xref target="RFC7556"></xref>. <vspace
            blankLines="1" />In a typical deployment scenario, these
            provisioning domains are owned by the same provider (see Section 1
            of <xref target="RFC8803"></xref>). Such a deployment is meant to
            seamlessly use both fixed and cellular networks for bonding,
            faster hand-overs, or better resiliency purposes.</t>

            <t>Each of these provisioning domains assigns IP
            addresses/prefixes to the CPE and provides additional
            configuration information such as a list of DNS servers, DNS
            suffixes associated with the network, default gateway address, and
            DOTS server's name <xref target="RFC8973"></xref>. These
            addresses/prefixes are assumed to be Provider-Aggregatable (PA).
            </t>

            <t>Because of ingress filtering, packets forwarded by the CPE
            towards a given provisioning domain must be sent with a source IP
            address that was assigned by that domain <xref
            target="RFC8043"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="rcpe"
            title="Typical Multi-homed Residential CPE">
            <artwork><![CDATA[               +-------+            +-------+
               |Fixed  |            |Mobile |
               |Network|            |Network|
               +---+---+            +---+---+     
                   |                    |     Service Providers 
       ............|....................|.......................
                   +---------++---------+     Home Network    
                             ||                   
                          +--++-+ 
                          | CPE | 
                          +-----+ 
                                ... (Internal Network)
                            
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sc2"
               title="Multi-Homed Enterprise: Single CPE, Multiple Upstream ISPs">
        <t>The scenario shown in <xref target="scmi"></xref> is characterized
        as follows: <list style="symbols">
            <t>The enterprise network is connected to the Internet using a
            single router.</t>

            <t>That router is connected to multiple provisioning domains
            (i.e., managed by distinct administrative entities).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Unlike the previous scenario, two sub-cases can be considered for
        an enterprise network with regards to assigned addresses:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>PI addresses/prefixes: The enterprise is the owner of the IP
            addresses/prefixes; the same address/prefix is then used when
            establishing communications over any of the provisioning
            domains.</t>

            <t>PA addresses/prefixes: Each of the provisioning domains assigns
            IP addresses/prefixes to the enterprise network.</t>

            <!--CJ: a third sub-case could be a combination of the above two, because of organizational considerations, for example. I would explicilty mention this additional context.-->
          </list></t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="scmi"
            title="Multi-homed Enterprise Network (Single CPE connected to Multiple Networks)">
            <artwork><![CDATA[               +------+              +------+
               | ISP1 |              | ISP2 |
               +---+--+              +--+---+     
                   |                    |     Service Providers
       ............|....................|.......................
                   +---------++---------+     Enterprise Network           
                             ||     
                          +--++-+ 
                          | rtr | 
                          +-----+ 
                                ... (Internal Network)
                            
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sc3"
               title="Multi-homed Enterprise: Multiple CPEs, Multiple Upstream ISPs">
        <t>This scenario is similar to the one described in <xref
        target="sc2"></xref>; the main difference is that dedicated routers
        are used to connect to each provisioning domain.</t>

        <!--CJ: this context is also privileged for mixing PI/PA addresses, imho.-->

        <t><figure anchor="mcmi"
            title="Multi-homed Enterprise Network (Multiple CPEs, Multiple ISPs)">
            <artwork><![CDATA[                         +------+    +------+
                         | ISP1 |    | ISP2 |
                         +---+--+    +--+---+     
                             |          |     Service Providers
       ......................|..........|.......................
                             |          |     Enterprise Network
                         +---+--+    +--+---+
                         | rtr1 |    | rtr2 |
                         +------+    +------+
 
                               ... (Internal Network)
                            
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sc4" title="Multi-homed Enterprise with the Same ISP">
        <t>This scenario is a variant of <xref target="sc2"></xref> and <xref
        target="sc3"></xref> in which multi-homing is supported by the same
        ISP (i.e., same provisioning domain).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="DOTS Multi-homing Deployment Considerations">
      <t><xref target="dep"></xref> provides some sample, non-exhaustive,
      deployment schemes to illustrate how DOTS agents may be deployed for
      each of the scenarios introduced in <xref target="msc"></xref>.</t>

      <texttable anchor="dep" style="all" title="Sample Deployment Cases">
        <ttcol align="center">Scenario</ttcol>

        <ttcol align="center">DOTS client</ttcol>

        <ttcol align="center">DOTS gateway</ttcol>

        <c>Residential CPE</c>

        <c>CPE</c>

        <c>N/A</c>

        <c>Single CPE, Multiple provisioning domains</c>

        <c>Internal hosts or CPE</c>

        <c>CPE</c>

        <c>Multiple CPEs, Multiple provisioning domains</c>

        <c>Internal hosts or all CPEs (rtr1 and rtr2)</c>

        <c>CPEs (rtr1 and rtr2)</c>

        <c>Multi-homed enterprise, Single provisioning domain</c>

        <c>Internal hosts or all CPEs (rtr1 and rtr2)</c>

        <c>CPEs (rtr1 and rtr2)</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>These deployment schemes are further discussed in the following
      subsections.</t>

      <section anchor="dcpe" title="Residential CPE">
        <t><xref target="dotsrcpe"></xref> depicts DOTS sessions that need to
        be established between a DOTS client (C) and two DOTS servers (S1, S2)
        within the context of the scenario described in <xref
        target="sc1"></xref>.</t>

        <t>For each provisioning domain, the DOTS client MUST resolve the DOTS
        server's name provided by a provisioning domain (<xref
        target="RFC8973"></xref>) using the DNS servers learned from the
        respective provisioning domain. IPv6-capable DOTS clients MUST use the
        source address selection algorithm defined in <xref
        target="RFC6724"></xref> to select the candidate source addresses to
        contact each of these DOTS servers. DOTS sessions MUST be established
        and MUST be maintained with each of the DOTS servers because the
        mitigation scope of each of these servers is restricted. The DOTS
        client SHOULD use the certificate provisioned by a provisioning domain
        to authenticate itself to the DOTS server(s) provided by the same
        provisioning domain.</t>

        <t>When conveying a mitigation request to protect the attack
        target(s), the DOTS client MUST select an available DOTS server whose
        network has assigned the IP prefixes from which target
        prefixes/addresses are derived. This implies that if no appropriate
        DOTS server is found, the DOTS client MUST NOT send the mitigation
        request to any other available DOTS server.</t>

        <t>For example, a mitigation request to protect target resources bound
        to a PA IP address/prefix cannot be satisfied by a provisioning domain
        other than the one that owns those addresses/prefixes. Consequently,
        if a CPE detects a DDoS attack that spreads over all its network
        attachments, it MUST contact both DOTS servers for mitigation
        purposes. </t>

        <t>The DOTS client MUST be able to associate a DOTS server with each
        provisioning domain. For example, if the DOTS client is provisioned
        with S1 using DHCP when attaching to a first network and with S2 using
        Protocol Configuration Option (PCO) when attaching to a second
        network, the DOTS client must record the interface from which a DOTS
        server was provisioned. DOTS signaling session to a given DOTS server
        must be established using the interface from which the DOTS server was
        provisioned.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="dotsrcpe"
            title="DOTS Associations for a Multihomed Residential CPE">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[                          +--+
                ----------|S1|
              /           +--+
             /    DOTS Server Domain #1  
            /
      +---+/  
      | C |
      +---+\  
            \ 
             \
              \           +--+
                ----------|S2|
                          +--+
                  DOTS Server Domain #2
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multi-Homed Enterprise: Single CPE, Multiple Upstream ISPs">
        <t><xref target="dotsmcgms"></xref> illustrates a first set of DOTS
        associations that can be established with a DOTS gateway, which is
        enabled within the context of the scenario described in <xref
        target="sc2"></xref>. This deployment is characterized as follows:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>One of more DOTS clients are enabled in hosts located in the
            internal network.</t>

            <t>A DOTS gateway is enabled to aggregate and then relay the
            requests towards upstream DOTS servers.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>When PA addresses/prefixes are in use, the same considerations
        discussed in <xref target="dcpe"></xref> need to be followed by the
        DOTS gateway to contact its DOTS server(s). The DOTS gateways can be
        reachable from DOTS clients by using an unicast address or an anycast
        address.</t>

        <t>Nevertheless, when PI addresses/prefixes are assigned, the DOTS
        gateway MUST send mitigation requests to all its DOTS servers.
        Otherwise, the attack traffic may still be delivered via the ISP which
        hasn&rsquo;t received the mitigation request.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="dotsmcgms"
            title="Multiple DOTS Clients, Single DOTS Gateway, Multiple DOTS Servers">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[                               +--+
                     ----------|S1|
    +---+          /           +--+
    | C1|----+    /     DOTS Server Domain #1         
    +---+    |   /
+---+      +-+-+/  
| C3|------| G |
+---+      +-+-+\  
    +---+    |   \ 
    | C2|----+    \
    +---+          \           +--+
                     ----------|S2|
                               +--+
                       DOTS Server Domain #2
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>An alternate deployment model is depicted in <xref
        target="mcms"></xref>. This deployment assumes that:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>One or more DOTS clients are enabled in hosts located in the
            internal network. These DOTS clients may use <xref
            target="RFC8973"></xref> to discover their DOTS server(s).</t>

            <t>These DOTS clients communicate directly with upstream DOTS
            servers.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>If PI addresses/prefixes are in use, the DOTS client MUST send a
        mitigation request to all the DOTS servers. The use of anycast
        addresses to reach the DOTS servers is NOT RECOMMENDED.</t>

        <t>If PA addresses/prefixes are used, the same considerations
        discussed in <xref target="dcpe"></xref> need to be followed by the
        DOTS clients. Because DOTS clients are not embedded in the CPE and
        multiple addreses/prefixes may not be assigned to the DOTS client
        (typically in an IPv4 context), some issues may arise in how to steer
        traffic towards the appropriate DOTS server by using the appropriate
        source IP address. These complications discussed in <xref
        target="RFC4116"></xref> are not specific to DOTS.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="mcms"
            title="Multiple DOTS Clients, Multiple DOTS Servers">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[       ..........                   
       .  +--+  .      
 +--------|C1|--------+                
 |     .  +--+  .     |      
+--+   .  +--+  .   +--+
|S2|------|C3|------|S1|
+--+   .  +--+  .   +--+
 |     .  +--+  .     |     
 +--------|C2|--------+     
       .  +--+  .
       ..........    
      DOTS Client 
        Domain          
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Another deployment approach is to enable many DOTS clients; each of
        them is responsible for handling communications with a specific DOTS
        server (see <xref target="scms"></xref>).</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="scms"
            title="Single Homed DOTS Clients">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[       ..........           
       .  +--+  .      
 +--------|C1|  .              
 |     .  +--+  .
+--+   .  +--+  .   +--+
|S2|   .  |C2|------|S1|
+--+   .  +--+  .   +--+
       ..........
      DOTS Client 
        Domain  
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Each DOTS client SHOULD be provided with policies (e.g., a prefix
        filter that will be against DDoS detection alarms) that will trigger
        DOTS communications with the DOTS servers. Such policies will help the
        DOTS client to select the appropriate destination DOTS server.</t>

        <t>The CPE MUST select the appropriate source IP address when
        forwarding DOTS messages received from an internal DOTS client. If
        anycast addresses are used to reach DOTS servers, the CPE may not be
        able to select the appropriate provisioning domain to which the
        mitigation request should be forwarded. As a consequence, the request
        may not be forwarded to the appropriate DOTS server.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multi-Homed Enterprise: Multiple CPEs, Multiple Upstream ISPs">
        <t>The deployments depicted in Figures <xref format="counter"
        target="mcms"></xref> and <xref format="counter" target="scms"></xref>
        also apply to the scenario described in <xref target="sc3"></xref>.
        One specific problem for this scenario is to select the appropriate
        exit router when contacting a given DOTS server.</t>

        <t>An alternative deployment scheme is shown in <xref
        target="mcmgms"></xref>:<list style="symbols">
            <t>DOTS clients are enabled in hosts located in the internal
            network.</t>

            <t>A DOTS gateway is enabled in each CPE (rtr1, rtr2).</t>

            <t>Each of these DOTS gateways communicates with the DOTS server
            of the provisioning domain.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>When PI addresses/prefixes are used, DOTS clients MUST contact all
        the DOTS gateways to send a DOTS message. DOTS gateways will then
        relay the request to the DOTS server. Note that the use of anycast
        addresses is NOT RECOMMENDED to establish DOTS sessions between DOTS
        clients and DOTS gateways.</t>

        <t>When PA addresses/prefixes are used, but no filter rules are
        provided to DOTS clients, the latter MUST contact all DOTS gateways
        simultaneously to send a DOTS message. Upon receipt of a request by a
        DOTS gateway, it MUST check whether the request is to be forwarded
        upstream (if the target IP prefix is managed by the upstream server)
        or rejected.</t>

        <t>When PA addresses/prefixes are used, but specific filter rules are
        provided to DOTS clients using some means that are out of scope of
        this document, the clients MUST select the appropriate DOTS gateway to
        reach. The use of anycast addresses is NOT RECOMMENDED to reach DOTS
        gateways.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="mcmgms"
            title="Multiple DOTS Clients, Multiple DOTS Gateways, Multiple DOTS Servers">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[                 
                         +---+         
            +------------| C1|----+                
            |            +---+    |      
+--+      +-+-+      +---+      +-+-+      +--+  
|S2|------|G2 |------| C3|------|G1 |------|S1|
+--+      +-+-+      +---+      +-+-+      +--+ 
            |            +---+    |     
            +------------| C2|----+     
                         +---+           
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multi-Homed Enterprise: Single ISP">
        <t>The key difference of the scenario described in <xref
        target="sc4"></xref> compared to the other scenarios is that
        multi-homing is provided by the same ISP. Concretely, that ISP can
        decide to provision the enterprise network with:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The same DOTS server for all network attachments.</t>

            <t>Distinct DOTS servers for each network attachment. These DOTS
            servers need to coordinate when a mitigation action is received
            from the enterprise network.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In both cases, DOTS agents enabled within the enterprise network
        MAY decide to select one or all network attachments to send DOTS
        mitigation requests.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>DOTS-related security considerations are discussed in Section 4 of
      <xref target="RFC8811"></xref>.</t>

      <t>DOTS clients should control the information that they share with peer
      DOTS servers. In particular, if a DOTS client maintains DOTS
      associations with specific DOTS servers per interconnection link, the
      DOTS client SHOULD NOT leak information specific to a given link to DOTS
      servers on different interconnection links that are not authorized to
      mitigate attacks for that given link. Whether this constraint is relaxed
      is deployment-specific and must be subject to explicit consent from the
      DOTS client domain administrator. How to seek for such consent is
      implementation- and deployment-specific.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require any action from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Roland Dobbins, Nik Teague, Jon Shallow, Dan Wing, and
      Christian Jacquenet for sharing their comments on the mailing list.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Kirill Kasavchenko for the comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6724'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8811'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4732'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8973'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4116'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3582'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8043'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7556'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dots-rfc8782-bis'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8783'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8903'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8803'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
